Farewell, Earth
The ship that is departing is
The Space Battleship
Yamato
It departs now to Iscandar,
at the end of the cosmos,
bearing its fate.
"We will come back, no matter what it takes"
Answer with a smile to the waving people
Going far from the Galaxy towards Iscandar
A faint gleam of hope
The Space Battleship Yamato
It's just stupid... And a smart girl like you?
I made the wrong decision.
Let's get going.
Thank you very much.
Doctor, is it true that Yuki is an Iscandarian?
That's even stupider.
These were her thoughts...
...as she entrusted her sister with a dangerous mission.
You may learn the truth during your voyage.
But do not let that sway you.
Until we meet again, safe travels.
The salvation of all intelligent life...
That is the path of Iscandar...
We are already thirty-five days behind schedule.
But if we use this subspace gate,
we can shave off 30,000 light years.
The system satellite that controls the gate is near.
The question is whether we can take control of it.
The core contains records of a race...
A race, which controls the system satellite, different than that which built the gate.
Who controls it?
It contains their name, as well.
Out with it.
It was Garmillas.
I was seconds from destroying the Yamato. Why have you recalled me?
What's going on?
Early this morning, our Leader's ship was destroyed through sabotage.
Lord Desler has been assassinated.
Only two people knew he would be visiting Balun.
One is Admiral Ditz, the Supreme Commander of Astrofleets.
And the other is yourself.
You are here because I am accusing you of plotting the Leader's assassination.
That's crazy!
You and Ditz worked to assassinate the Leader and take control of the Empire, yes?
I've no time for childish fantasies.
Fantasies, are they?
Even though your wife has been arrested?
Elisa? What has she done?
You didn't know? She's been part
of an anti-government movement.
There must be some mistake!
That's what everyone says.
Order is the foundation of any nation, and it must be maintained.
For that to happen, anyone suspected of wrongdoing must be punished.
There can be no exceptions.
Gimleh...
I shall take a vote. Gentlemen of the jury?
Death! Death! Death!
By unanimous verdict, the tribunal sentences General Domel to death.
We're set to leave for the naval review. Has something good happened?
Domel has been sentenced to death...
Congratulations, sir!
Launch the fleet. Our target is Balun!
Stay in line.
Stop!
Get up.
Anyone attempting to run will be shot on the spot. Understood?
Is that the one?
Yes.
Is that the subspace gate?
It doesn't look functional...
Can it really propel us tens of thousands of light years at once?
Yes.
No way...
Even I can't do anything with it.
However, at this rate, it will affect ship functions.
Is maintaining the ship a doctor's duty?
It is not.
Anyway, explain...
Why do this? It isn't like you.
Why didn't you tell anyone?
Normally, you would have.
Orders from Central Command...
That isn't what I'm asking!
"You need the courage to disobey an order you believe is wrong."
I once told Kodai that.
We should have been honest with ourselves.
I will assume full responsibility for its disclosure.
I'm disappointed that Mori's an alien.
Yeah, really...
I was a fan!
The Type 100 is ready to go!
Thanks.
I'm ready.
Even if Kodai went for protection, why would the XO take Mori?
Maybe it's because she's an Iscandarian?
That's not true! She is not!
But she had that message from Starsha...
She also has no memories from over a year ago.
Stop speculating!
We're in the middle of a mission. No talking.
The Type 100 has entered the system satellite.
There don't appear to be any booby traps.
Looks like a long-abandoned base.
If the inertial mass system is on-line, the rest must still be functional.
This could be useful. We'll bring it back on board later.
Let's get this done.
I don't know which way to go.
Yeah...
Didn't you say a civilization older than that of Garmillas made this?
So it seems.
Do you think they'd be upset that the Garmillans have tainted it?
"The sadness of being tainted makes the snow fall once more," huh?
What's that?
Chuya Nakahara.
I once knew someone who loved that poem.
Wasn't he a twentieth-century poet?
A poet from over two hundred years ago?
Is that...
What?
Do you think the Iscandarians knew about this Nakahara guy?
Could the Iscandarians have known such an ancient poet?
Be quiet!
Looks like they left guard dogs.
There may be more.
This way.
He always was that way...
Whenever I didn't know what to do, he'd show me the way.
-Seven Years Ago - AD 2192-
Here are the papers you requested.
Thank you.
It appears that the alien fleet has reached Mars.
So I hear...
The rumor is they've upgraded Inner Planet War shelters, and everyone's evacuated.
Don't worry.
Kodai?
They'll soon be starting a big operation to defend Mars.
Where did you get that information?
It's a secret.
So, what do you want? You can't enter this lab without permission.
Do you have permission?
I...
I'm bringing materials Sanada requested.
Same here.
Here.
You said you'd like to read these.
A book of poems?
Yes...
I thought equations were his only interest.
Yeah.
I mean, no!
Anyway, Kodai, your friend is here.
That's right! I promised to meet my brother!
Bye.
He does whatever he feels like, doesn't he?
He's honest with himself.
You could learn a thing or two from him.
Kodai...
Honest with yourself?
I'm glad I was able to prove you're an Earthling.
I mean, you have to be, right?
But then, why don't I have any
memories from beyond a year ago?
Is it just a coincidence that's when Yurisha disappeared?
Well...
It is not.
I should have told you.
You and Yurisha were involved in the same accident.
Whether an accident or terrorism... No one really knows.
But in that incident, you lost your memory, and Yurisha went into a coma.
We did all we could, but she never woke up.
Why didn't you tell us?
We still don't know where in the Large Magellanic Cloud Iscandar is.
But we have the map they sent!
That's right. That data's been entered
into the Automatic Navigation System.
And the location doesn't exist.
She showed us the path to Iscandar. Or she was meant to.
Wait! But then, how could we have come this far?
We've followed her memories...
You can't mean.
Yurisha is the core of the Automatic Navigation System.
We've been searching for Iscandar by tracing her memories.
But...
I know that it's ethically wrong,
and that we must take responsibility.
And that's why we will bring her home safely.
That's part of the Yamato's mission.
Then that message capsule...
Why did I have it?
Because...
Nice work.
Let's get inside.
Inside?
This is our goal.
The system satellite control area.
It's open.
The rest of this is my job.
You wait here.
XO Sanada! XO Sanada!
XO Sanada!
Just as I thought.
If we restart the system satellite, we can open the subspace gate.
Neutron Radiation: High
Do you want to lock bulkhead D?
It's been locked from inside.
Kodai, listen to me.
It appears that restarting the system will cause a massive neutron burst.
Then...
But this area is shielded.
In other words, you'll be safe there.
What about you?
Is it shielded?
It is, right?
What are you doing?
It's dangerous! Stop!
No! Don't!
I'll try to undo the lock myself.
Open the door, Sanada!
Kodai, I said I had a friend who liked Chuya Nakahara's poetry, right?
That friend was Mamoru Kodai.
Your brother, Mamoru Kodai.
You were my brother's friend?
Yes, best friends.
-Six Years Ago - AD 2193-
If you're looking for her, Niimi's gone.
Another meteorite. This time on Rio de Janeiro.
Clearly, they're being sent by the enemy.
The aliens have changed their strategy.
Hey, want to get some air for once?
The sky looks terrible.
There may be a nuclear winter.
After you graduate, you're joining the Cosmo Navy?
Yeah, how about you?
Me... I'm not cut out for the military.
But I think there must be something I can do.
You'll find something...
You'll find something I couldn't do in a million years.
A poem and an equation. Those are what we are.
We both wish to protect this world in different ways.
In that respect, we're the same.
Yeah.
"The sadness of being defiled,
causes snow to fall once more."
Sanada!
He was my friend, and I...
I couldn't tell him that Operation M was a decoy,
that the whole fleet was a decoy.
-10 Months Ago - Far East Sector Underground Dock-
The operation will begin at 0630 in the morning.
Good luck, Captain.
We will now begin loading the prototype torpedoes.
The operation begins in the morning.
I don't know how many ships will make it in time.
But we'll take out Pluto.
Did you get to see Niimi?
We broke up.
I see.
I never got the chance to return this.
You can have it.
No, I'd like you to keep it.
I've read it twice, and I still don't
understand why anyone likes poems.
You don't hold back, do you?
The fact that it was a decoy operation was top secret.
I didn't have the courage to tell my friend.
I just obeyed my orders.
That's the kind of man I am.
Even if he'd known, he would've gone.
No matter what the situation...
No matter how unreasonable the order.
If he'd decided to do it, he would.
That is how my brother was.
Yes, that's the way he was.
Mamoru, your brother is following in your footsteps.
Sanada, I...
I didn't know my brother liked poetry!
Just a little more...
"The sadness of being tainted longs for nothing.
The sun sets helplessly with the sadness of being tainted."
Sanada, what made my brother happy?
What made him sad?
Neutrons have flooded the control room.
No one could have survived it.
Sanada!
The door is open...
This is the path to the mother world.
XO!
Where are you, Sanada?
I wanted to learn more about my brother.
And more about you!
Sanada!
Neutrons don't pass through water easily.
You really do amaze me...
Chuya Nakahara Poems
Attention all crew. The gate is online.
The Yamato will now be able to jump 30,000 light years.
But before we do, I must make something clear.
There is a rumor about an Iscandarian aboard this ship.
It is true.
But she is not a crew member.
She is asleep in the automatic navigation room.
You are Yurisha Iscandar?
No, now I am myself.
I am Yurisha of Iscandar.
Out of the Forest of Memory
Episode 17
No matter how steep or far the road is
I will not give up
Endless tears flowing down my cheek are not
A white flag of surrender
I go and become the wings of a loved one
Gather up the shattered dream
And take it to the end of the universe
Steady as she goes!
Row strongly
And hold your thoughts close to your chest
Steady as she goes!
Through your despair
A ray of light shines
Balun. A lighthouse in space.
The center of a network that connects the galaxy.
A gigantic enemy fleet gathers, numbering 10,000 in all.
The Yamato sets a course straight through for the Large Magellanic Cloud.
Next time: Over the Black Light.
There are 273 days left before humanity is extinct.